Preliminary Inventory to the Carl and Helen Winter Papers TAM.583
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
- IV, Political Activities
  - Winter, Helen: Printed Materials and Clips Relating to the Peace Movement (New Stockholm Peace Appeal), Circa 1975-1977 (Box 6)
  - Winter, Helen: Remarks to Ideological Conference of CPUSA, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Winter, Helen: Speech at Third Annual Dinner of Jewish Affairs, Jan 12, 1975 (Box 6)
  - Winter, Helen: Speech to German Communist Party (GCP), Oct 1978 (Box 6)
  - Winter, Helen: "Standards for Party Leadership," Party Affairs (With Letter from Reference Center for Marxist Studies), Jan 1973, Aug 1993 (Box 6)
  - Winter, Helen: "The US People and Foreign Policy" (Draft of Article for World Marxist Review and Correspondence with John Pittman), Dec 1975-Feb 1976 (Box 6)
  - Winter, Helen: World Assembly for Peace and Life, Against Nuclear War (Prague): Conference Materials, Clippings and Correspondence, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Young, Coleman: Memorial and Obituaries For, 1997 (Box 6)
  - Young Communist League, USA: "Fight the New Right-Wing Congress - An Open Letter to the Youth and Student Movement ...", 1990s (Box 6)
  - The Working Woman, March 1933 (Helen Allison on Cover), Mar 1933 (Box 6)
- V, Smith Act Trials and Defense Work
  - "The Amnesty Campaign" (4 Page Memo to National Committee to Win Amnesty for Smith Act Victims, Author Unknown), Circa Jun 1953 (Box 6)
  - Amter, Sadie Van Veen: "Women Courageous (Certain Lines for Helen Winter and Esther Jackson and Edna Winston), Circa 1953 (Box 6)
  - Bachrach, Marion: Amnesty (With Attached Letter Signed by Six Michigan Smith Act Defendants), 1953 (Box 6)
  - Bloor, Ella Reeve: "Salute to the Wives of the Twelve Leaders", Circa 1949 (Box 6)
  - Cattmar, Nell: "Millions of People Will Help Little Michele" (Letter to Helen Winter), Circa 1955 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress (New York): Conference Call, Ephemera, Press Release, Trade Union Committee to Protest the 12 Smith Act Indictments, Circa 1949-1954 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress (Pittsburgh): Pamphlet on Steve Nelson and Pennsylvania Smith Act Defendants, Circa 1953 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress of Illinois: Fact Sheet in the Case of Claude Lightfoot, 1954 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress of Los Angeles: CRC Bulletin, Apr 1952 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress of Michigan: Bulletin for Action: "Save the Rosenbergs", Circa 1948 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress of Michigan: Labor Defender, Oct 1953-Apr 1954 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress of Michigan: Smith Act Fight Back Campaign, 1952-1953 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress of Michigan: Smith Act Fight Back Campaign: "Fact Sheet #1 On Smith Act" (TS, 25 pp), Circa 1953 (Box 6)
  - Civil Rights Congress of Michigan (Helen Winter): Fund Raising for Smith Act Trials, 1954-1955 (Box 6)
  - Committee to Keep McCarthyism Out of Michigan (Civil Rights Congress), 1953-1954 (Box 6)
  - Communist Party USA: Newsletter Containing Copy of Indictment of Twelve Communist Leaders, Circa 1949 (Box 6)
  - Communist Party USA National Education Commission: "Outline on New Stage in Struggle for Peace" (Discussion Material), May 1953 (Box 6)
  - Connecticut Volunteers for Civil Rights: Ephemera Related to Connecticut Smith Act Trial, Circa 1954 (Box 6)
  - Crockett, George: "Memorandum Re: Second Indictment" (of Carl Winter), Jan 22, 1953 (Box 6)
  - Crockett, George (As Agent for Hortense Allison): Receipt for Bond for Carl Winter, Mar 1, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Davis, Benjamin J. vs. Herbert Brownell, Attorney General of the United States and James Bennett, Director of the Bureau of Prisons: Petition Against Segregation in Prisons, Early 1950s (Box 6)
  - Dennis, Eugene et al. vs. United States of America: Full Text Supreme Court Opinions in the Case of the Communist Leaders June 4, 1951 (Annotated by Carl Winter), Early 1950s (Box 6)
  - Dennis, Eugene et al. vs. USA: Motion for Leave to File Supplemental Petition for Rehearing and Supplemental Petition, Sep 27, 1951 (Box 6)
  - Dennis, Eugene et al. vs. USA: Petition for Leave to File and Memorandum of Amici Curiae in Support of Petition for Rehearing, Sep 27, 1951 (Box 6)
  - Dennis, Eugene et al. vs. USA: Petition of Defendants to the Honorable Judge Harold R. Medina, Mar 11, 1949 (Box 6)
  - Dennis, Peggy: Memo on Parole Petition for Smith Act Prisoners, 1950s (Box 6)
  - Draft of Article for Press on Denial of Parole for Carl Winter and Other Communist Leaders (Revisions by Helen Winter), Circa 1953 (Box 6)
  - Essay on Response of American Public to Smith Act and Anticommunist Measures, Jun 30, 1955 (Box 6)
  - Families of the Smith Act Victims (Michigan), 1952-1954 (Box 6)
  - Families of the Smith Act Victims (Michigan): Hortense Allison's Notes On, 1952-1954 (Box 6)
  - Families of the Smith Act Victims (National), 1952-1954 (Box 6)
  - Fehlhaber, Elmer: "The Dialectic of Providence" (TS Dedicated to Smith Act Defendants), Jan 12, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Gordon, David: "A Letter to Carl" (Typescripts of Poem), Circa 1951-1953 (Box 7)
  - Gordon, David: "Paul Robeson and Other Poems" (MSS), Dec 1951 (Box 7)
  - Harlien, Mary Ann: Notes for United Press Article on Helen Winter, Circa 1953-1954 (Box 7)
  - Le Sueur, Meridel: "Double Jeopardy" [?]: TS for Pamphlet on Families of Smith and McCarran Act Victims with Edits by Helen Winter and Anna Ganley (39 pp), Circa 1953 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Committee for Protection of the Foreign Born, 1953-1955 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Council for Peace: News of Peace Newsletter, Flyer on Korean War, Jan 1953 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Committee to Win Amnesty for Smith Act Victims (Carl Haessler), Circa 1952-1953 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Smith Act Defendants: Holiday Cards, 1950s (Box 7)
  - Michigan Smith Act Defendants and Families Committee: Latest Facts on the Appeal to the Supreme Court Against Michigan Smith Act Convictions, Mar 1956 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Smith Act Trial: List of Exhibits, Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Michigan State Committee of the Communist Party: "For Defending Your Rights ... This Man Got 30 Days in Jail" (Carl Winter), 1948 (Box 7)
  - Michigan Worker: Request for Information, Dec 10, 1963 (Box 5)
  - Minnesota Committee for Amnesty for the ASmith Act Victims (Meridel Le Sueur), Jul 1952-Aug 1952 (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Smith Act Notes and Clippings, 1950s (Box 7)
  - National Committee to Win Amnesty for Smith Act Victims, 1952-1953 (Box 7)
  - Oral Argument of Dorothy Forest in Support of Motion to Dismiss the Indictment Against St. Louis Smith Act Defendants, Apr 17, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Organizing Committee for Prisoners Welfare Committee (Michigan): Invitation to Social Evening and Birthday for Carl Winter, Early 1950s (Box 7)
  - People's Conference to Repeal the McCarran Act: Petition to Congress to Repeal the McCarran Act, Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Political Victim's Welfare Committee: Pamphlet on Chicago Smith Act Victims (Lilian Green and Doris Fine), 1950s (Box 7)
  - "Problem Offenders" (1 pg TS on Communist Prisoners), 1950s (Box 7)
  - Provisional Committee for Amnesty for Benjamin J. Davis, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Provisional Trade Union Committee for Repeal of the Smith Act, Circa 1952 (Box 7)
  - Sacher, Harry: Press Release with Attached Letter to US Attorney General Protesting Discrimination Against African American Prisoners (Benjamin Davis), Oct 1951 (Box 7)
  - "Some Legal Questions" (TS, 2 pp), Circa 1953-1954 (Box 7)
  - Song Lyrics About McCarthyism and Smith Act Trials (Some by Helen Travis), Circa 1950s (Box 7)
  - Sugar, Maurice: Invitation to Discussion on Smith Act, Circa 1950s (Box 7)
  - UAW-CIO (Michigan): Letters in Support of Michigan Smith Act Defendants from Amalgamated Local 351 and Ford Local 600, Feb 13, 1956 (Box 7)
  - UAW-CIO 14th Convention: Resolutions Against Smith Act and in Support of Amnesty, Circa 1953 (Box 7)
  - United States District Court, Eastern District of Michigan: Notice of Opening of Smith Act Trial on October 13, 1953, Aug 28, 1953 (Box 7)
  - United States of America vs. William, Z. Foster, et al.: Election Not to Serve Sentence Imposed, Oct 26, 1949 (Box 7)
  - USA vs. William, Z. Foster, et al.: The Grand Jury Charges, Circa 1948-1949 (Box 7)
  - USA vs. Saul Laurence Wellman et al.: The Grand Jury Charges, Circa 1953 (Box 7)
  - USA vs. Saul Laurence Wellman et al.: Defendants' (Thomas Dennis') Brief on Question of Guilt by Association, Circa Jan 1954 (Box 7)
  - USA vs. Saul Wellman, et al.: Letter from Bondsman to Helen Winter Re: Procedure for Leaving Jurisdiction, Aug 19, 1953 (Box 7)
  - United States of America vs. Carl Winter: Application to Extend Bail Limits in Order to Visit Father (Carl Weissberg), Jun 29, 1956 (Box 7)
  - USA vs. Carl Winter: Chronological List of Proceedings, Circa 1955 (Box 7)
  - USA vs. Carl Winter: Grand Jury Charges, Circa 1948 (Box 7)
  - USA vs. Carl Winter: Transcript of Proceedings, Jul 30, 1948 (Box 7)
  - USA vs. Carl Winter: Indictment, Oct 26, 1948 (Box 7)
  - United States of America vs. Helen Mary Winter: Transcript of Proceedings on September 18, 1952, Sep 18, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Peggy: Letter of Appeal to Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Feb 26, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul, Nat Ganley, Tom Dennis, Billy Allan, Phil Schatz and Helen Winter: "Greetings From Smith Act Defendants", Circa Feb 1954 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence et al. vs. United States of America: Appelants Supplemental Brief, Mar 2, 1955 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence et al. vs. USA: Brief for Appellants (Filed by George Crockett and Ernest Goodman), Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Memorandum for the Government, Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Motion to Proceed Forma Pauperis and Petition for Writ of Certiorari to the US Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, Circa 1956 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Notice to Dismiss Indictment and Cancel Bond, Circa 1958 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: On a Petition for a Writ of Certiorari to the US Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit: Memorandum for the US, Feb 1956 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Order of Judge Frank Picard to Dismiss Indictment, Sep 16, 1958 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Petit Jury Panel, Oct 6, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Summary of the Activities of Helen Winter Drawn from Larger Government Document (19 pp), Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Court's Decision on Appeal (US Court of Appeals), Nov 18, 1955 (Box 7)
  - Wellman, Saul Laurence, Thomas Dennis and Nat Ganley: Petition to Frank Picard to Voluntarily Dismiss Himself as Judge, Oct 21, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl: "12 Times 12 Million" (Speech to National Committee of CPUSA), Dec 9, 1948 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl: Inventory of Belongings Seized Upon Arrest, Jul 20, 1948, Feb 14, 1949 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl: Parole Appeal (Press Release, Clip, Letter to Supporters from Helen Winter), Feb 1953-Mar 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl: Press Release on Forty-Sixth Birthday Celebration and Greetings from Bill McKie, Maurice Sugar and Bob Travis, Sep 1952 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl: "Proposed Line for Smith Act Defense" (Interview), Jun 18, 1949 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl: Subscription to Civil Rights Congress (Copy), Jun 30, 1950 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Correspondence Course for Auto Technician, Circa 1951-1956 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Diploma in Toolmaking, Aug 10, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Envelopes Bearing Tally of Correspondence, Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Legal Services Agreement with George Crockett, Dec 9, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Mail Regulations, Circa 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Notebook, Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Notes, Dec 31, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): List of Recently Published Books, Circa 1954-1955 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Notice of Action of Parole Board (Parole Denied), Mar 24, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Notice of Warrant for Arrest, Detainer, Mar 29, 1954, Oct 8, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Parole Application (Copy), Dec 26, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Prison Administration Forms (Blank), Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Prison Administration Newsletters, 1952, Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Reading List and Research Notes with Occaisional Clippings, Jul 1951-Oct 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl (Prison Documents): Receipts and Accounting, 1951-1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Carl: United States Board of Parole: Certificate of Conditional Release, Feb 15, 1955 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Accounting Notebook, 1952-1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Appeal to Have Carl Winter Transferred to Milan Prison, Oct 1953-Nov 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Description of Arrest Of (TS, 1 pg), Undated (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Draft of Article on Helen Winter's Illness and Smith Act Trial, Circa 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Letter to the Editor of the Daily Worker (Draft), 1950s (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Notes and Speeches from Amnesty Campaign for Carl Winter and Others, Circa 1952 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Notes for Remarks at Dinner to Support Parole and Amnesty for Henry Winston and Gilbert Green, Circa 1955-1956 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Notes From Michigan Smith Act Trial, Including Draft of Final Statement to Judge Picard, Circa Oct 1953- Feb 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: "Overt Acts" (Document from Michigan Smith Act Trial), Circa Oct 1953-Feb 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Stenobooks From the Smith Act Trial, Nov 1953-Dec 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Stenobooks From the Smith Act Trial, Nov 1953-Dec 1953 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Stenobooks From the Smith Act Trial, Dec 1953-Jan 1954 (Box 7)
  - Winter, Helen: Typescript of Closing Remarks of Billy Allan (Incomplete) and Helen Winter from Smith Act Trial, Feb 1954 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Carl Winter: Clippings (Copies), Apr 1948-Oct 1949 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Mar 1952-Sep 1952 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Oct 1952 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copy and Original), Nov 1952 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies and Originals), Jan 1953 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Mar 1953, Sep 1953 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Oct 1953 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Nov 1, 1953-Nov 15, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Nov 16, 1953-Nov 30, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Dec 1, 1953-Dec 15, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Dec 16, 1953-Dec 29, 1953 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Jan 1954 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Feb 1, 1954-Feb 15, 1954 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Feb 16, 1954-Mar 1954 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Copies), Aug 1958-Oct 1958 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trials: Clippings (Copies and Originals), 1950s (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Carl Winter: Clippings (Originals), Apr 1948-Oct 1949 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Mar 1952-Sep 1952 (Box 7)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Oct 1952 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Sep 1953-Oct 1953 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Nov 1, 1953-Nov 15, 1953 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Nov 16, 1953-Nov 30, 1953 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Dec 1, 1953-Dec 15, 1953 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Dec 16, 1953-Dec 29, 1953 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Jan 1954 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Feb 16, 1954-Feb 28, 1954 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Mar 1954 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Aug 1958-Oct 1958 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter: Clippings (Originals), Feb 1, 1954-Feb 15, 1954 (Box 8)
  - Smith Act Trials: Clippings (Originals), Undated (Box 8)